Hit the record.
So let me share the...
Mm.
So, let me guys know if I,
I guess I need to make it larger.
Is it good?
Good, good, yeah.
The...
All right.
So, we want to start from...
Okay, from the top.
So,
we were just going to go through your
comments, Varun, right?
Or you wanna...
Either ways,
I mean I have a few high-level comments.
We can go through my comments.
But if we, I, I don't know,
do you have any thoughts.?
It's more complicated than I expected it
to be because I expected it to be that
Did the.
you will have similar to what we're doing
for say DSS scan.
Where you just have a single function
that takes a configuration token,
and the contract of that function is that
it returns a chunk or the stream part,
whatever we want to call it.
Are you going to API or NO?.
Uh,
I'm talking about the implementation with
the with the stream index and all that
stuff in the MQD messaging.
So, for example,
do you have an example of a function that
Yep.
would refer to implementation RTC?
That would be a string function.
Yeah,
at the bottom of the document there is a.
net sketch section in the.
No, no, I'm saying, like,
do you have an actual example, like,
Oh.
for example, schema? Okay,
let's say it's let's say schema registry
Application that uses this.
downloading a schema with the schema is
too big, right? So, what I would expect,
I what my assumption was that it would be
something like,
instead of having schema registry get
schema,
which it takes a request and returns a
response,
it would be get schema streaming.
Which takes a request and returns a
response, where the request includes, say,
index, what you call the stream index,
and the response includes index,
what you call the stream index.
I was guessing in the case of schema
request,
you don't need the request to be streamed
on the response,
so the request would just be standalone,
and then the response would have the...
Chunk and the index,
and so your get request would take the
response index for the next chunk to
query is my expectation.
Can I?
Can I say something slightly different?.
So I think what Arnav is saying here.
EK.
What's also not clear to me is what the
application looks like.
So I asked for the POC,
but I think what we also need,
I believe an application where we start
with the what.
You say this is an application executor
which needs to expose streaming API.
This is all the what looks like,.
This is all the executor code looks like,
this is all the invoker code looks like.
I think that will give us a pretty good
idea of how that code is going to look
like.
So I think we have some specifics of the
API,
but I have some other comments because
again it's not clear to me.
How the protocol is established,?
What are the headers that invokers needs
to send,?
What are the headers that executor needs
to send, it's all there in words.
But if you ask me,
then at least it's not clear to me from
the read that I gave it that when an
invoker now wants to invoke a streaming
API,
how does it know this is a streaming API
versus regular RPC? How does it,?
What does it do differently?
What are the headers that it includes?.
What are the headers that the response
includes,
how and then you know how that exchange
flows.
There are several concepts which are
introduced which all make sense
individually,
but then how it fits together I think is
not clear to me from this talk at least.
And I'll admit I didn't go very deep into
those 3 sequence diagrams.
I didn't realize it was a separate ADR.
I think we should model the two,
but even quickly going through the 1st
sequence diagram here, I don't understand.
I mean,
I think in the second sequence diagram,
I think you have some stream ID or
something. The first one doesn't have.
That. So.
OKI.
Maybe that's something that you can
clarify for us.
Yeah, let me try. So let me sure.
Different.
I'll show you the whole screen, so...
Uh...
So...
Do you do you do I need to make it larger
or it's fine?
I can come closer.
Good for me.
Okay.
So this is the...
Sort of.
Entity relation class diagram for the all
the abstractions introduced.
So we have streaming invoker,
streaming executor.
Invoker open the exchange,
Executive serve the exchange, and...
Exchange consists of two.
Like changes a specific message that gets
sent.
The first message that is sent in the
stream.
which must be data message,
initiate the exchange.
Okay.
So there is no handshake.
The first data met. OK, so.
Okay.
So Exchange consists of two
unidirectional streams, right?
So one from the...
Invoker to execute it in the reverse
direction.
So...
So, each stream.
Ahh.
So it carries stream entry.
Each stream entry can be of three types,
data type, control type, and status type.
Um...
The way it is communicated,
what type of message it is, is,
give me one sec. I have it down here.
So it is, oops.
We use a stream user property.
Uh, we sure have...
PyPI.
Yeah, there is examples of this.
So data type would look like,
I guess I'll make it larger.
would look like the value of that stream
property would be D0 and T is the stands
for the timeout.
So.
So, first data message opens the exchange,
and then together with data messages,
some control messages can flow through
the same.
What are we looking at here?
What is this diagram Maxim?
It is a anatomy of that stream property
value.
So there is under score under score
stream header that you're proposing.
Yes.
OK,
there's not just going to be a stream
header.
It has, you're saying it has a data form,
control form, status form. Okay,
what is the data form?
What is the control form?.
When do I send control form?
When do I send?
Status form do I send all at the same
time?.
I think it seems like I send one at a
time.
Yes, those are mutually exclusive forms.
Okay.
So when do I send control,?
When do I send data?.
So...
Data you send when you, as it.
Says you want to say data message,
so we have index of that message in the
stream,
and then time out goes only when in the
direction from invoker to execute.
Basically,
invoker control that time out of.
Got it, got it. So now I'm invoker.
I'm sending this thing. Actually,
can we start with the what?
What does the what look like?.
What we have not defined what for this.
I mean,
there isn't a watt like for the protocol.
But that's the first thing, folks.
Like we don't have a watt for RPC or
telemetry. You have a watt for them,
like how you use those.
Yeah,
but what does you know how RPC looks like
in a ward, right?.
What like, but that's a.
Like use of RPC,
so it wouldn't like the what wouldn't
describe like the stream value or
anything like that.
I think what describes the payload inside,
right? The request response structure, no,
Right, just the payload.
What if?
No, but OK, so not not necessarily, right?
. Like, how do I know this API,
not this.
the streaming is gonna have a stream
response?.
Coming over.
These are completely separate clients,
so a streaming invoker is not the same
thing as an RPC invoker.
Look.
Correct,
but how do I know which one to use based
on the what?
Because I'm going to generate my client,
code Gen. my client.
We would need to define another type
within Watt for that, I think,
Well...
similar to the RPC.
This.
That's what I'm asking for.
Yeah,
that this is not something not something
That's the interface right.
we've defined yet.
Then I think we should start that,
I would say,
because that's going to be our API.
That's where it should start, but OK.
Let's take a note.
Let's see if we need to do that.,
But okay, now I'm invoker.
I know this is a stream request and
response. Okay,.
Now I'm sending my first message.
Uh.
And I add a header, call under score,
under score stream with the value D and
index is 0,. Is that correct?.
Yes, uh, you know, one second, ohh,
go back, where's that?
At.
Only one header, that's it.
I think, yeah, yeah, here we can,
we can actually,
it's a better demonstration here, so yeah,
invoker application starts subscribes for
Right, that sounds...
A.
the.
Ohh.
the topic and then publish first request
with this stream property set as a D0 and
T and then timeout and.
And T is what time out, OK?,
That's the one that came from the invoke
It is.
streaming command.
Yes, that's the whole exchange timeout.
So,
is what you supposed to time in in in
what you supposed to finish the whole
communication?
Got it, got it, OK.
And.
And that invoke streaming, sorry,
just to be clear,
invoke streaming command.
Seems like it passes in a stream,
is that is that the proposal it's taking
in a stream?
I didn't see that.
Uhh...
Yes, yes,
this is invoker takes stream and receives
Six.
Okay.
a stream from the executor.
Got it. OK, keep going.
All right,
and then like the first message came to
the receiving part of the executor.
At that moment, in Walker already.
One question,
what is that other partition P?.
What is P there?.
P. It's a some.
Yeah, good in our case.
It's the client ID of the invoker side.
Yeah.
It's part of the RPC protocol that we
used on the regular invoker and executed.
Ah, find ID and going oversight. Perfect.
OK, that works. OK, makes sense.
Alright,
and then when the communication is
established,
then the messages can flow on in any
direction, like in like.
In any.
No, no, no wait, so, so,.
So the first message went through.
And the subsequent messages will just
increment the D equal to 1, two, three,
and so on, right?.
And the T will be reduced by the SDK.
Yes,
T will be the current value of the time
that left on.
So each party going to have their own
timer, like a...
Invoker starts its timer when the first
message successfully published to the
broker receiver starts,
executor starts its own timer based on
the time it received from the invoker.
So basically there will be two clocks
ticking altogether,
but each message is still going to carry
that.
A current value in case executed dies and
new one starts,
so it so it knows how much is left,
and basically that would be the new
execute.
portion of the timeout that left for it
to complete the communication.
So, yeah,
this T is dynamic for updated in each.
Okay, correct.
And we don't have TE and MRPC, right?.
G.
We are adding it here. For MRPC,
we just use the message timer or the MQT,
yeah, message timer.
In regular RPC,
like a request and response are like,
Ohh.
Right?.
like here you might have be,
the application might be doing something.
So like the idea of resuming a stream
with a different executor has different
semantics in the middle of a stream
versus a different executor getting a
different invocation on a like a more
atomic RPC.
So there's more considerations to be made
about like these kind of things as a
result for the resiliency story.
Makes sense.
All right, then. Now,
when messages are flowing,
it's up to the application side to decide
either like response on any on each
request or wait for the whole stream to
be completed to send the response or vice
versa.
OK, sorry, I have one.
Ahh.
More question:,
What is identifying this stream versus a
different stream?
If you have two streams in parallel?.
What do you mean?
The core correlation ID, right?
Yes, Karangula.
Yeah, there's a correlation ID.
Same as RPC.
OK, yeah, perfect. OK, makes sense,
makes sense, makes sense. OK, perfect.
And a quick word on nomenclature here,
a stream exchange refers to like a
individual like relationship of an
invoker and an executor exchanging data,
like that's a stream exchange,
and then a particular message sent within
that, like a...
piece of the stream,
we're calling a stream entry.
OK, got it.
And then exchange can be completed in
four ways, I believe.
So the graceful completion is when each
side sends the special,
this command version, not the version,
command type.
This is the see the command packet is
being sent for the first time.
Yes, well, yeah, in the normal flow,
this would be the first time C message
type is sent to signal the last message
in the stream.
So it does not carry any data,
it just signal that there will be no more
data messages.
And why can the last message just not
have the additional header last?
And...
There is a special explanation.
I don't recall it from top of my head
right now. Tim, if you, if you...
Yeah, yeah,
so the gist of it is that we need to be
able to distinguish between customers
ending the stream with a message that has
no payload versus customers ending the
stream without sending another message.
Their payload,
their payload might always be empty,
for instance.
Got it.
I guess what what is saying is,
in this last data message,
can we have just another flag that
indicates that this is the last message
in the data stream?
Why do we need to have a separate message
for that specific?
But the.
No, I understand that,
and this is something we've considered.
OK.
Abdelwahab.
That's, I think,
one of the last sections in the doc,
Ohh.
and it's mostly around that case where
user sends no payload for that last
message.
Do we count that as a stream entry,
or do we just say that the stream is over
at that point?
It's kind of a confusing scenario, so...
For us,
it makes more sense to mandate that the
final flag there is in its separate pack,
separate stream entry.
Varun,
are you asking why it's part of the under
score under score stream header and not a
different property?
Is that what you're asking?
No, I'm asking what Vadim said. Basically.
I'm still trying to rock.
I don't understand what even Vadim were
asking then.
So, I think I know what you're getting at,
Varun.
And maybe this is a helpful explanation
of like where the disconnect might be is
that I think based on the comments I've
seen from you on a PR,
that you're kind of thinking this in
terms of like a chunking scenario,
that you're sending a finite amount of
data
broken up over a series of messages.
Whereas this document is a more generic
approach maybe because the resiliency
story of chunking versus string,
like there's a case where you might be
streaming data that's losable.
I, I...
And at that point, there may not be a,
the endpoint may not be triggered by the
end of.
data,
the endpoint might be triggered by some
of the application choosing to end an
arbitrarily length stream at a certain
point. Thus,
the need to differentiate between data
Yeah, I, you're right,.
You're probably right. Like,. I get what?
and control.
You're saying. OK,. I mean,
I see the reason why you would want this,.
Where I just like some external trigger
tells me that there is nothing more to be
sent,.
So I just send a control packet which
says last, because I'm done.
Or says that I know that this is going to
be my last message. OK, I mean,
we could support both maybe, but OK,
this is fine for the simplification that
it provides.
Alright, after, after.
Okay, you're right, Carter,.
I get what you're saying.
Okay, after the last message received,
then this stream,
data part of this stream is considered
closed.
So we don't expect any data message on
that stream,
but the stream is still functional and we
can receive some control messages and
In some cases,
status messages on this on that stream.
So then, other.
Okay.
Just to be very clear,
in this you said control two,
that should be control zero. I mean,
it's just a.
We have,
we have this index is through all the
messages, so it's a universal counter.
Oh, across the data and control,
I see it's the same,.
The index is the control, I see.
Yeah,
so idea behind it is that we have this
status message that actually when it
sends status,
it refers to the index of that message,
like opposite message that is the status
report on. So.
But we'll get there.
So then the other party sends the same
Kar.
message back and everybody agree that
communication is over and behave like.
in a way that the application defines it.
So the cancellation,
in case one party wants to cancel,
it sends...
Ah.
Sorry, is it the status measure?
I didn't quite get that.
Are you going to be talking about it or
should I ask my questions now?.
Uh, you should ask your questions anyway.
OK,.
So just to be so just so I understand,
so every for the entire stream on the
invoker side,
I will have the sequence number always
incrementing.
That thing is a sequence number.
And it will be incrementing from zero
onwards,
whether it's a data packet or a control
packet.
A DRC only indicates whether it's a data
packet or a.
Control packet.
If it's a control packet,
then you should have some other thing
like a last or cancellation or something
like that, which goes along with it.
That metadata is the relevant one.
Otherwise, it's a regular data thing;
this thing continues to improvement,
and the status message is sent when.
So, and the current.
version of that specification.
We have status message to the canceled
status message.
Uhh...
But cancel is a status or a control.
If I understand correctly,
status is about a particular chunk, right?
Yeah, that's.
Or a particular segment,
whatever you want to call it.
So a particular response entry,
I believe is it.
So the fact that you want to respond to a
particular entry being 499,
that is where you specify as zero,
which means the 0th.
No, in.
Entry of the other side.
No, they, they, they, no,
that's so the candle cancel status is
sort of special,
so index here meaningless.
The status,
the cancel status message used to signal
the desire of one of the parties to
cancel.
So we used to have a control message like
that we first send control, cancel,
and then the response was the cancelled
confirmation from the other party of the
cancelled.
But then we decided that...
It we actually can use the only we can
use the status message for both
confirming and asking for cancellation.
Since.
Basically,
it wouldn't make much difference for this
scenario to have like a...
OK,.
So so is cancer only use so is status
only use for cancer?.
Yes.
I see. Is that returned? I just missed it?
.
I thought.
It, I do it.
It's used for other errors too, right?
Yeah,
I thought this was how we signaled like
protocol violations back.
If user sends message 10 that has some
weird shape to it, the executor can say,
hey, status error on message number 10.
Protocol violation sort of thing.
Yeah,
I believe that would that was my
recollection as well.
Yes, that's what I was also saying.
Yeah, that.
Like...
But then I do see in the doc that it says
cancellation support the index is 0 and
has no meaning,
which is what Maxim was also saying,
so I'm confused.
Different status messages.
That.
At least for the completeness of the doc,
can we include it in the doc? I mean,
to assume that other people like me are
not going to remember.
Yes, okay, okay.
So slightly above it under table one is
where it says S colon 1 colon 10 and here
it has an error about the received
message at index one. So yeah,
I think the doc is just contradicting
itself.
And is that is just a HTTP status code,
so...
No,
but it's I guess I think it's pretty much
the same status code. It's not the it's.
It's what we have in regular RPC,
I believe.
Model.
Yeah, so...
Is is the.
So what is it meant to be then?
Is status supposed to be per entry or is
it per exchange?
No, the status we don't send,
so success is implicit.
So basically we don't respond status on
every message. It just...
Yes, so I'm asking in general,
is a status message meant to be for an
entry or for an exchange?
Yes, it's per entry.
Okay,
so it's just that for cancel you
specifically say as zero.
Yeah, because...
How do you know?
How do you know it's a cancel versus
something else?
Well, there is this status,
when I get 499.
So what would be the example for status
message that's not cancelled?
How would you distinguish it?
So that would be like there would be
would be the index, well index.
Like 0 can be also,
but that's the status user property would
What?
have some different error code.
The reason I'm trying to think of it is
I'm thinking of how you are going to
parse it in the implementation,
like in the SDK or the generator code or
whatever it is.
So you're going to see it's S,
which means it's status.
Then you're going to read an integer,
but you don't know what to do with that
integer yet.
Then you're going to read the under score
under score stat.
Then you're going to figure out, okay,
based on the under score under score stat,
if it is 499,
then I throw away the integer. Otherwise,
I keep the integer and then I process it.
Is that the flow chart?
Yes.
Is that ideal?
It was like wanted.
Ohh.
Okay, sure, sure. I guess it's the same,
it's what I thought Varun was asking
about the last message as well earlier,
which is that in the last message,
it's part of the under score under score
stream, but it's concatenated with colon,
but here under score under score stat is
a whole separate property.
Also, in a bunch of places,
you're saying that, for example,
for D&C misses,
you're saying that the sequence number is
the same, like it's the same set,
same sequence.
So like the next control message will
have an integer that's higher than the
previous data message. But then that case,
the D and the C comes before the integer.
It's kind of.
Weird, but anyway,
I guess it's all possible in the end,
doesn't matter.
We.
Okay,
you folks should definitely continue to
discuss, and I think Arnav,
you are on the right track there.
For just one second,
because I need to draw the schedule a
meeting that I need to attend,
but can you click on that link I just
posted in the chat, Maxim?.
Sure.
Okay,.
So I think these in my mind are the
boundary conditions, right?
Like what happens when before
disconnection and recovery,
when Invoker drops connection,
reconnect same session.
I think we kind of understand,
but let's be clear,
same thing with executor.
And then Invoker crashes, loses session,
Invoker crashes,
reconnect to the same session but loses.
Date, which I think is possible,
and same with the executor, or we say,
okay,? This is illegal, not supported,
but I think,
can we define what happens for each of
these scenarios?
Sure.
When this happens, midstream.
And then maybe I'm missing some more
boundary conditions which I don't.
I guess this one other comment I added
was I think somewhere you say, oh,
the executor could wait for the entire
stream to complete before responding,.
But then I think we need to consider some
things like the broker receive maximum
and things like that.
Where maybe we just say the app needs to
know and take care of it and we cannot
really help, which is fine,
but I think then let's state that very
explicitly.
But those I think are going to be
scenarios that we'll have to worry about.
You're saying whether responding includes
not just the MRPC response,
but also the backs for the request.
I believe there was some discussion that
we had about that regarding acknowledging
message. Like there's a set,
there's a whole section about
acknowledgement, I believe,
and how you can acknowledge an individual
stream entry as it comes in.
So you can wait to respond.
to the stream until you've gotten
everything,
No.
Um...
but you can still acknowledge the parts
of the stream that you have received thus
far,
so they don't have to live on a broker
forever.
And then the executor crashes and you
lose it.
The downside of that is that, right,
the downside of that is if you crash and
restart, then those messages,
those earlier chunks will not get you
something.
That's why it's opt-in.
Like you have to choose to acknowledge it.
So it gives you time to write to disk or
whatever you may need to do as a backup.
I mean, sure,
but I think the point here is that we
need to define that, right?.
We need to say, look,.
We don't recommend you doing it.
We can always say the application
developer needs to be super smart and do
everything all by themselves,.
But I think the whole idea is that we
need to, say, okay, don't do this.
We don't want you to do this because
these are the limitations there.
Awesome.
Something like that.
It's not even that simple because from
the executor's point of view,
it doesn't know how big the invoker's
quest is going to be.
So how can the executor decide should it
make it should it act them or not?
Exactly.
Correct. So I mean at that point,
maybe the best thing is to...
Yeah, yeah.
Have a way to, like,. If you crash,
then have a way to signal that, OK,.
This is a stale stream,.
I'm gonna crash it,
so the invoke a reset is the whole thing,.
Maybe that's the best way to do it.
Which they do have,
because they can define that we have the
correlation.
They know that it's a it's a half of a
Correct, totally,.
But we need to write it down.
stream which they don't have the setting.
I know it's possible,
but we need to define.
Right, right, right.
Okay.
I'll drop off, but please carry on.
But good, yeah, good start.
I think that's maybe Avishek,.
We should have one more session next week
with the same audience. And then we can.
Sure, yeah, I'll just go there one more.
Very.
So,
my comment in the beginning about it
being more complicated than what I
expected, so Maxim,
if you can check the chat of the of this
meeting, so earlier above,
so when I posted the code block and then
Valerie and Carter said,
the reason is because you want to have
the ability to have multiple responses to
be sent without.
Needing to request each response
individually.
which is fine if that's the reason.
I understand why it's been designed this
way.
So my question is why is that the
requirement?
Is it just because you want to be
efficient,
you don't want to send multiple,
you don't want to keep requesting the
next chunk of the response,
or is there any other reason?
I'm sorry,
I that's too far too fast for me. I don't,
I don't, like,
what can can can you come again, maybe,
The.
or Tim, if you...
So,
you're you're asking about like the
pattern of request and response here,
Arnav?
Yes, yes,
because so the way you guys have designed
the API is that essentially the streaming
is transparent, right?
You don't need to know ahead of time
whether the request or the response is
going to be streamed or not.
You can automate it based on the
existence of the under score under score
stream parameter. And secondly,
it's also handled automatically, right?
from an application's point of view,
you don't care whether the incoming
request is streamed or a single thing
that contains the entire payload because
it can be handled automatically.
My question was the alternative which I
was thinking is that it would be where
the streaming is explicitly part of the
API.
So if you look at the code block which I
pasted there.
It has the, let's say,
the imagine the current API for schema is
you have a request to a response,
which is a single request containing the
UV and single response containing the
whole JSON schema, whatever it is.
And the new streaming API would be where
you have a request,
which is the UV and optionally a
configuration token,
and then the response is.
The chunk of that response, and obviously,
and so this is what I expected it to be,
and so then Valerie responded that the
reason you are not doing it this way is
because you want to be able to have
multiple responses without needing to
request each response one by one,
so you want to be able to send a request
with a and then you, whether you get one.
response or five responses which all
together make up the schema,
it's supposed to happen automatically,
which is fine because that means that you
don't need to keep on request response
number two, request response number three,
request response number four,
it happens in one shot. My question is,
is this the only reason that you have
done it this way,
that you want it to be efficient?
You want to request one of the classes
without needing to explicitly request
S.
them, or is there any other use?
There was a couple other reasons I think.
And they had to do with GRPC, right?
Because GRPC allows for full
bidirectional streaming.
So when you're doing like full
bidirectional streaming, then you know,
you,
there doesn't have to be a correlation
between what's being sent from one end to
the, or I mean,
I'm sure it's correlated on some level in
the application, but there's not a one.
to one response happening, right?
Like maybe you send a response every five
messages or like, you know,
maybe the expected situation,
Yeah, that's fine.
All of that is all of that is encompassed
in having all of that is encompassed in
like because the GRPC,
the GRPC spec is very large, so.
having a function that takes a request
and returns a response.
The response can be empty.
The request can also be empty.
Sure,
then there'd be two separate things and
then yeah,
it's just a lot of extra traffic.
Maybe there was other reasons.
Yes, so again, again,
that's what I'm asking.
Is the extra traffic the only reason or
is there any other reason?
It's a combination of the extra traffic
as well as, you know,
at the same time supporting these
bidirectional streams without like having
to create whole new like paths,
code paths,
because now you don't have to have this
like,
because there's just two arbitrary
streams going both directions, you can.
you don't have to have these specialized
code paths for responding in the
affirmative to the invoker in addition to
acting to the broker.
It's simpler implementation and it's more
efficient on a wire.
Can anyone think of any other reasons
we'd gone this way?
I can't fully remember.
I think also just so it can be more
variable, right?
I think the canonical example that we
talk about a lot is like requesting a
video stream. So you're saying like,
you know, tell me,
show me this camera feed for an
indeterminate amount of time for the next
5 minutes.
So it's not like you really need to
request each additional frame,
you're just getting them as the camera
sends them.
Yeah,
that that's the that's the efficiency
reason. OK, if there's another reason,
that's fine.
Yeah.
I'm not saying there has to be another
reason.
I'm just asking if there's some
requirement. OK, thank you. Yeah,
go ahead, Vadim.
I guess I already answered my own
question, but just to confirm,
in this scenario where you send one
response,
one request and getting multiple
responses,
the client's application will still
receive those chunks as individual like
responses, right?
You will not basically wait until the end
of the stream before returning it to the
client.
Correct.
Correct, yes.
Okay.
In fact,
we don't even really think about them as
Okay.
chunks because they're not necessarily,
like they could be,
each part of the stream could be a
standalone component,
like A-frame of a video, right?
You don't have to wait for all the frames
Yes.
to see the video.
You can see them dynamically.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Make that makes sense,
and I guess I have just overall a
question. I, I, I,
I guess it's for the backend part reasons,
but now we will have two different
clients.
We have like old RPC client and now the
streaming client.
Do we want somehow to obstruct it so?
Volvo.
Why is it? Why is it a new client?
Isn't it just adding the capability of
No, who?
interpreting the under score under score
tree to the existing client?
I think just Tim to mention it will be
completely different executed.
At.
Yeah.
It would be different.
The resiliency story is completely
different on this.
Like they'd be functionally completely
different code paths.
It would just like pollute the
implementation.
It makes more sense to have individual
like envoys for doing this rather than
trying to put this completely separate.
implementation is conceptually similar,
but is implementation wise completely
separate inside the existing on voice
source code.
Doesn't really make much sense.
It makes more sense. Like, I mean,
even like the relation, like,
despite the fact that it's an invoke and
an execute, right?
Like the ergonomics of it are completely
different. So.
Like putting them side by side doesn't
really make a lot of sense because there
isn't necessarily a lot of transferred
code styling or anything.
But does that mean every API is going to
be the new one,
regardless of whether it makes sense to
be streaming or not?
So to be clear,
there's two levels we're talking about,
right? There's like the protocol envoy,
and then there's what would surface
through, say, schema registry, right?
So in the example that you posted, Arnav,
you're talking about like the schema
registry service surface, right? Which,
yeah,
that could be on the same schema registry
client,
but that would be using a different.
envoy under the covers right at the
protocol layer.
Yes.
Pant.
Yeah, I guess my point is,
for all the clients, or let's say,
for customers who want to use our SDK,
for them it would be just that they
should always want to start with a
streaming API,
just in case they need that functionality
rather than start with a simple.
Invoker Executive,
and then convert it into the stream.
So I will say that the streaming invoker
and executor APIs will be far more
intimidating than our normal RPC APIs.
No one's going to want to start with that.
Yeah, yeah, it's the complex.
The complexity is significantly higher
here,
and even if you were to use the same
envoy, right,
and like you wouldn't be able to use the
same code structure,
because like the way of dealing with it
is going to look completely different,
because there's just because of the
additional complexity Tim is talking
about.
The way of dealing with it is different
makes sense,
because now instead of having a single
request response,
you have to deal with the request stream
and all response stream. So,
Exactly.
so from your even your own applications
point of view,
instead of doing a simple function,
you will now have to do an iterator or
stream or whatever. That part I get,
that part I get.
Exactly,
your application code's gonna be
completely different, so, like,
there's no,
That I get.
there's no better migration story by
putting it on the existing on voice.
No, no, no,
so that is the one step further than what
I'm saying.
So what I'm saying is I understand that
if you want to have, say,
the ability to handle streaming requests,
you have to write your code differently
because now instead of getting one
request,
you will have get a stream and you have
to extract the chance from it yourself
and then maybe aggregate them yourself or.
write them to discover whatever that part
I get. The question is, if I am like an,
if I am writing my own schema registry,
so how do I choose to decide whether I
want to use the scheming one or the
streaming one or the non-streaming one?
Wouldn't I always use the streaming one
because that gives more flexibility to
clients?
Exactly.
I guess that was the question I wanted to
You certainly.
ask. Thanks, Arnav. Yeah.
You could, but again,
it's not intuitive to do such a thing,
especially if you're just doing basic
one-to-one request response.
Yeah, if you want one-to-one,
it's simpler to do it with the existing
Setting up a stream.
So, so, so it would be, so let's say,
so are you going to have like two
ones.
different grades or two different APIs or
two different like modules in the SDK or
how is it going to work?
two different,
two more envoys within the RPC module of
But, but...
Okay.
the crate.
Okay, so what might happen is that I,
at the schema registry server,
might choose to use the streaming one,
and then that allows both streaming and
non-streaming clients to send the request
to me. Or I might choose, sorry.
No.
To be clear,
streaming executor cannot handle vanilla
RPC.
We're not trying to bake that in in any
Yeah.
Okay.
But this is a great example.
This is a great example of a schema
way.
I see, okay.
registry because it maps perfectly to
request response semantic,
but it requires streaming underneath in
case you have a large schema. For example,
you can deploy a broker with a low memory
profile and you cannot have schemas more
than 4 megabytes in size, right?
And this is a perfect scenario where,
as a as a developer,
you would want to start with a with a
streaming API right away to protect
against those scenarios,
even though your pattern is basically
request response,
so but streaming underneath has.
I.
So I want to circle back to the whole
chunking verse.
Yeah.
Is that what you were going to say,
Valerie? Sorry,
I shouldn't have jumped in.
Yeah,
I think that that's a chunking example,
but go ahead.
Yeah, so the reason, the reason we keep...
Yes,
but but we we we we're solving chunking
with streaming, right?
Okay,
so the reason we keep bringing up this
distinction is there's a completely
different resiliency story between
chunking and streaming.
If you're streaming arbitrary length
things like a video with frames,
if you lose A-frame, whatever,
you don't care,
you just render the next frame, right?
In the case of chunking,
you need absolute data integrity of every
single message that came through to
reconstruct
the data, right?
These are fundamentally different stories
that have fundamentally different
resiliency behaviors.
So.
Mm.
So,
are you saying that there is a different
So.
way to implement the schema registry
chunking than using streaming?
In my opinion,
you have to do a like a much more,
much less efficient something that maybe
even built on top of RPC. Again,
that's not what we've really been talking
about here.
It.
OK, wait, wait, wait, stop,.
Stop for a minute, so sorry, sorry,.
Let me jump in real quick.
So, so.
But.
I thought it was so when Chang King was
streaming, okay?
I just want to confirm one thing though,
Varun,
OK.
just to confirm that the schema problem
is not going to be solved by streaming.
Yu.
It is 100% gonna be strong by streaming.
That's what we are doing is defining
streaming for.
The 3 top scenarios for streaming right
now are streaming images,
large WASM images that don't fit in one
impurity message, scenario, one.
Scenario 2, asset detection.
Where I have many assets that I want to
detect and send at the same time.
Instead of saying, you know,
The thing is going to say detect assets,
I'm going to send 10 discovered assets at
the same time. Again,
that does the streaming thing.
The third scenario is I have a camera
capture media image and it's too large.
I want to send it over MQTT.
For whatever reason and tap it,
but still don't want to do it,.
Then you'll use it.
None of those scenarios are going to be
the streaming in true sense in the sense
I'm getting an audio file and I'm going
to play it here,
or I'm getting a video and I'm playing it
here, or yeah, drop a few chunks,
none of those matter.
Those are not the scenarios that we have,
at least not that I know of.
We are absolutely going to implement
chunking on top of this.
That's why we are doing streaming first,
because streaming is a more generic form
of it.
I think we should think about it that way.
Well...
I mean, if, if that's what you,
if what you want is purely chunking,
then you know,
and we say that streaming is going to be
for chunking,
then we do shut the door to this more
flexible approach in terms of data
resiliency. Like, if you,
if you want streaming to have the
guarantee of...
every single no lost data,
like that means you can't have like
executors pop up to replace other ones
midstream.
We order.
Like there's a whole set of new error
conditions that appear.
We are in the business of no data loss.
Since day zero.
We cannot assume data loss is okay and
design anything.
There might be some scenarios where
customers might say, hey, this is okay.
If you lose a couple of frames,
but we cannot assume that.
I don't think in industry.
So if you want to shut the door on that
permanently, then this changes the...
The.
I'm not saying so permanently,.
I'm saying that there might be some
scenarios where it's okay,
but those are not going to be common,
just like MQT broker supports cost 1 and
cost zero.
Everywhere that we use,
we only use cost one,
but we support cost 0.
If you really want to use it.
You don't want to run it, but cost 1 is.
The is the this thing.
I also don't understand where the data
loss would happen,
Buddy.
Support.
even in the current situation.
Is the data loss happening because you
are not explicitly hacking every stream?
So you're saying that if, let's say,
D0 and D2 get delivered,
but D1 gets lost for any reason,
then nobody will know that D1 got lost.
Is that the data loss you report, Carter?
We're talking about like, okay,
so like the thing is like, let's say,
let's say in regular RPC,
we have this concept of like load
balancing and the idea that you can have
multiple executors running, right,
and then invoker hits and it gets load
balanced to different executors.
And if some of the executors go down,
the other ones that are still there are
still working, still handle the.
still respond to the request because
everything's atomic, right?
Everything's related, one request,
one response, executor gets it, cool.
The problem is that in the streaming
scenario,
streaming only works in the aggregate,
right?
At least if you need full integrity of
the entire stream. So the idea of an...
an executor goes down and another
executor picks it up like you have on RPC,
doesn't make,
because now the new executor doesn't have
Totally fine, which is totally fine.
You're absolutely correct,
the data that the original executor had.
Mhm.
and that's fine. So we can say that, look,
.
If an executor is processing a stream
request, and that executor goes down,
that request is entirely lost,
or that is considered canceled.,
And we define a way that it knows it's.
Needs to be cancelled.
The invoker needs to and it needs to
restart the stream again. That's OK.
Okay, because again,
that's a different story from our
But if none of that happens?
existing RPC story, right?
Like when we say RPC streaming, like,
you know,
the existing RPC has the support for that
I, I don't think so. I want to...
How is RPC story different at all?.
and now we're saying that we can't.
How is the RPC story different?.
because the RPC story isn't catastrophic
for an executor to go down.
If I send an invocation request.
Then if I send an RPC request and the
executor.
I think I think it's not it's not that I
wanted to clarify specifically that,
so if I understand how how it works right
now,
how how you guys SDK use this load
balancing,
you use partition key to basically route
to the specific executor and executors,
they use shared subscription and the way
how shared subscription are working right
now in the broker.
There is no such thing like if one
executor goes down,
the other executives will pick up those
requests. No,
it doesn't happen right now because the
shared subscription, there still will be,
the request will still be bounded to that
executor and they will be queued in that
executor session until executive restarts
and come back online. Then they can.
Yes,
for something that already got to the
It's true, but you can have some.
Yeah.
broker,
but we're talking about future messages,
right? Like it's not about the redelivery,
we're talking about future ones. So like.
It.
Oh no,
even future even future messages will go
In the future, future.
to the same session because it executors
use persistent sessions.
Right, right.
So, so Vadim,
what you're saying is correct,
but you can also imagine a degenerate
scenario where the session does expire or
something. So,
let's assume that the message is possible
Sure.
to be routed to a different, different,
yeah, but, but in that case, in that case,
Then they will time out the request,
the request will just time out.
what Varun is saying applies,
which is that you,
as from the server side,
you would be able to detect that this I
have received a request for which I have
no.
previous messages and so therefore I
should treat this as an orphan request
and then immediately cancel it.
Which is also what I was saying as well,
Yeah.
which is why I don't understand why there
would be a problem of data loss in this
There would not be, we just cancelled,
yeah, we just cancelled the request.
scenario.
Because it sounds to me that data...
It's not about data loss,
it's about stream loss because Varun is
The...
right that if, like, yeah,
you could just take down a whole stream
and start it all over again if anything
goes wrong, which is,
No, but again, this is this, no,
but again, this is.
it's just that that's not parallel with
the existing RPC.
So this was designed to have the
functionality.
Which is fine,. I'm not there is,.
I don't think we have said ever that the..
Again, it is just the,
this is the purview of the,
this is the purview of the executor,
right?
.
So the executor can decide whether it can
deal with the half request or not.
If it happens to be a video feed or a
camera feed or whatever,
then it knows that even if it gets a half
request, that's fine because it doesn't,
there is no state in the request response
exchange,
so it can just continue serving the
camera feed from whatever point it has
received the first request.
Or it might be the schema registry case.
In that case,
the schema registry stream cannot be
resumed. In that case,
you send the cancellation and you expect
the other side to send the request again.
It is up to the executor.
So that's what I'm saying.
I don't understand why it would
invalidate any of the scenarios that you
have in this document if you also
consider, yeah, now go ahead.
I.
No, no,
I was saying and completely agree with
Arnav,
but to kind of make it even more narrower,
if you want to say that, look,
this behavior when an executor goes down
is different from RPC,.
I have no concerns at all.
I don't think we have ever said that it
has to be exactly a one-to-one match with
MRPC.
I don't think that needs to be a goal.
It's totally fine if we say that, look,
in these cases,. If you want to do this,
either the executor cancels it or we
consider it cancelled because, you know,
we don't want,
there is no way you can start processing
1/2 stream. I mean, that's okay.
If you want to even narrow it further.
Yeah, I mean, if that's the requirement,
I mean,
we were just operating under the
assumption that we wanted the behavior of
Ek.
our PC that existed.
It's exactly like TSP stream versus UDP
stream, right?
It's you guys are implementing a UDP
stream,
but nothing prevents you from
implementing TSP stream on top of UDP
stream.
All you have to do is have either side
agree that we want this to be a TSP
Correct.
stream. That is,
we want there to be ordering of packets
and we want there to be no missing
packets in the middle.
And if there is an interruption,
then we consider the whole stream to have
failed.
That doesn't mean the underlying UTP
stream cannot be implemented. It can.
And it cannot be used. No, it can.
It's just that the ordering of...
in what you're calling the schema history
chunks,
that is an additional requirement on top
that both sides of the exchange agree to.
And so if we have that,
then that goes back to what we were
saying about the API implementation,
like how the server and the client use
the SDK, right?
So if I'm implementing the schema history
server,
I would want to use the streaming API,
whatever the SDK exposes,
so that gives my clients the maximum
flexibility,
because then I can send a streamed
request, sorry,
I can send a streamed response,
and I could potentially receive a
streamed request, though I guess for.
schema history,
there is never going to be a scenario
where you would need to get a streamed
request,
but hypothetically you could show why not.
And ideally that would then handle both
streamed responses as well as
non-streamed responses and streamed
requests as well as non-streamed requests.
Because why would it not?
So,
I understand that the current documents
satisfy the all the needs and just the
the the.
So, we...
The message integrity,
the request response integrity is the
problem of the application layer.
Is that what you're saying?
Yes.
I'm still a little skeptical that they
should be implemented on the same client
because of, like,
we'd have to do an inventory, I think,
before I'd be comfortable saying that
that's doable because of various caching,
dedupe, et cetera, logic.
Like this protocol is quite different
I, I...
from the original RPC.
Absolutely. And that's exactly Carter.
Why? I've been asking for the POC.
Ashing is really...
****.
And the POC needs to be for the scenario
that we are building this for.
And I wrote it there that this is not the
scenario. And I think, I mean,
I thought it was pretty clear,
but I also written a comment there.
I think last week where we need to
implement it for the scenario we are
building this for,
which is that there is a large file I
want to send it.
That's going to be the first scenario
we're going to use it for,
not only scenario, but the first scenario.
I did edit.
And those are the.
I did add this that that that scenario
into the POC, so yesterday there is a...
You did wait.
Support.
Fantastic.
Then I think once you have that,
then I think all these corner cases of
caching and deduping and all those things
will,
that's what we'll need to use to answer
that. How does it work?.
Well, so,
so I the one on the the extra thing on
top of what you're asking is how does the
user,
like the person who's writing the server
or the person who's writing the clause,
the client also use it?
Because this is the point that Vadim and
I were bringing up, right?
Like if I'm implementing the schema
history server,
do I use only the streaming API or do I
use only the single API?
Or if I use the streaming API,
does it handle both?
Or do I need to use two different ones?
And if I use two different ones,
MM.
what happens if I get a single request,
but I want to stream a response?
And I think that's why I was saying we
need to start with the what,
because my mental model Arnav,
is that the as a server.
Developer,
I choose whether an API has what? Like,
you know,? Is it like a GRPC, right?.
GRPC,
you have calls or you have the request
stream or response stream or request and
response stream.
But you know that up front,
you can look at the contact and then you
can know, hey,
this is what it's going to be.
But is that the case here or is the
streaming automatic?
That should be the case here is what I'm
saying, how do you use it otherwise?.
So, so we did,
so the code example which I had given,
Yeah.
where I had a separate API called request
streaming, that is what we want to have,
so you will have a single request that
only takes single request and return
single response,
and you will additionally have a request
streaming which takes streaming request
and return streaming response.
That's how I would think.
And if there is a better way to do it
then I would like to see it.
Is that the expectation you guys are
going with us all?
Yeah,
I think initially we came across this
question because on the invoker side,
you need to know at an API level if the
response will be streamed or not.
It's not something that the executor can
decide at runtime because the invoker has
to return some object that is either a
single RPC response or a stream of
responses.
Having the watt model certainly makes
that more ironclad.
Yeah, okay, that's fine. So in that case,
then for the schema registry example,
it would be that I would use both on
voice as you are calling them.
I would use one on voice for only for
single request single response and one on
voice only for streaming request
streaming response. Is that correct? Okay,
Yeah, yeah.
but then this again comes to the same
problem, right?
What if somebody sends a single request?
but my response is too big to fit and I
need to stream it. What happens?
It would have to be some kind of error
scenario that basically says, hey,
you need to send a streaming request,
even if there's only one request in that
stream.
Yeah, it has to be opt-in, so that,
especially for back compat.
No, but back compact is.
Okay,
back compat is so what I was thinking of
is that,
regardless of whether it's because the
fact that it's a stream is automatically
known by looking at the presence of the
under score stream header,
you could technically have a single
endpoint, basically,
which accepts both single requests and
streaming requests and is able to send
single responses as well as streaming
responses.
Mm-hmm.
But the back end part, I guess,
is violated specifically in the sense
that if you have an old client that does
not understand streaming responses,
then even if you send it a streaming
response, it will fail. Or worst case,
it will parse it as if it's a full
response and then it'll get confused.
So you want the streaming to be opt-in
for that reason. OK, I understand that.
So that means you would.
Would it be possible for the streaming on
why to support streaming responses,
but allow single requests,
or is that also impossible? Like,
could you treat single requests as if
they were a stream with one entry?
Also, Valerie,
where does the serialization fit into
this story?
I think it would be fine with just like
the bypass payload,
but will we run into an error with like
the predetermined like stream type,
or sorry, like data type?
because like executors are tied to a
specific data type.
Right.
So the idea of invoking,
doing a request response invocation
execution versus a stream, like.
The point is, yeah,
the envoy is tied to a to a output data
type,
which I don't think you could switch
Yeah, this is...
between them.
This is like another interesting thing of
the difference between streaming and
chunking, right?
Because like for chunking, you're saying,
well, once I reassemble all the chunks,
I have my data type. And for streaming,
Yes, yes.
you're saying per message,
I have a data type.
Like when you're talking about like a
video frame, right?
Like that might have some metadata and
you know, the video contents,
but like each of those is parsable.
And so I mean, you can't.
Like with streaming,
you can use the raw data type and say,
you know,
each piece can't be deserialized.
The customer's going to put it together.
But like,
But then the customer has to put it
together.
there is a little bit of a different.
Whereas if we did a dedicated chunking
implementation,
Yeah, with chunking,
we put it together for them.
we could put it together for the customer
using the predefined data type.
Yeah.
Yeah, but again,
we are not talking about chunking as you
are defining it.
So I'm fine with giving the customer the
frames, the individual chunks,
and letting them assemble it if that's
what they need to.
But that's not the question I'm asking.
The question I'm asking is if you have,
if I'm implementing the schema history
server,
currently what you're saying is I have to
choose to use both of the envoys.
I'm asking,
can I use just the streaming envoy?
and then have it work with both single
requests as well as streaming requests.
Such that,
in my from my application's code point of
view,
a single request just appears as if it's
a stream with a single entry.
I mean, I...
I don't want to speak at a turn and say
something that I don't,
without looking at it,
but I think the likelihood that your
stream and your atomic invoke are of the
same type. Also the invoke,
because the streaming is bidirectional
and invoke execute.
isn't.
There's a tight request response paradigm
on the original invoke with again tied to
data format where there's arbitrary,
like the bi-directional streaming,
there's a response type,
I guess it is just the response type,
but I think it is unlikely that they
would be the same. So you'd basically.
over,
your envoy would have to be tied to the
I...
type that you want back,
and then that's probably only valid for
one or the other.
I think sorry, but let me very quickly.
I think what Carter is saying, Karna,
is we cannot...
Yeah, I, I, I got that, I got that, so,
so...
I think in my mind,
the only way to do it in my mind, sorry,
just the only way to do it in my mind,
which can be like syntactic sugar again,
is to have two APIs, or maybe even one.
There's the streamed API,
Yes.
and then have a layer on top,
which is a chunking API,
which makes it seem like.
You're always using one of the other.
Yeah.
No, no, I got that part.
So I got that the chunking API is layered
on top of the streaming API.
That's what I was saying as well.
The question I was asking was
specifically,
is it possible to have different halves?
So like you can have a streaming response
by a single request.
And what Carter is saying is no,
you cannot. So it would mean.
No, no, no, that you can, of course,
that you have pieces support that in a
Well, yeah,
I don't want to say anything definitively.
request.
Like I haven't like really delved into
the implementation in a while.
EK.
So like I'm speaking off the top here.
It would still be considered streaming,
but yes,
you can have a single response in this
scenario.
No, it's the other way around.
So I am the server.
I'm using the executor to implement
schema history and I want to be able to
send a streaming response.
Does that mean I can only receive
streaming requests or can I receive
single requests as well?
It has to be the stream format.
There just can happen to only be one of
them, but like it still has to be.
Right,
so I can only receive streaming requests.
Yeah.
That's what I'm asking.
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah, yeah,
streaming invokers talk to streaming
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so it says.
executors exclusively.
We don't allow vanilla RPC invokers to
communicate with streaming executors.
Right, right, right, so, so, so, okay, so,
so, so, so, yes, so,
so what I was asking for cannot be done,
which is that,
so that means that if we want to have
this thing where we want to allow schema
to send responses that are larger than
fit in one entity payload,
we need the clients to update as well,
so that the clients need to start using
the streaming on my on their end.
So that they are able to understand
streaming responses and to so that they
Thanks.
can send streaming requests for schema.
Yes.
Okay, so if that is all the,
if that is all of the limitations,
then yes,
I can see why you want to have two
separate clients entirely.
And I understand that because the
streaming would be more complicated to
consume from a user,
you still want to make the non-streaming
unavailable. But basically, ideally,
if I am.
completely,
if I'm writing completely new code,
I guess I would always want to use
streaming just because of the greater
flexibility it gives me. Is that accurate?
Yes.
Greater flexibility, greater flexibility,
greater flexibility specifically in terms
I think so, yeah.
Maybe.
of message size. So, so sorry,
let me let you clarify.
If I am writing an API that is only
single request,
single response effectively,
as in semantically it is I send a request
and I get a response,
but I am unsure if my request or response
will fit in.
the single entity message.
I should always use the streaming API.
Is that correct?
So this comes back to, again,
like the idea of chunking a big message
But.
and like the predefined data types and
the idea that, in my opinion at least,
if we're worried,
if we're trying to send structured data,
like that is,
the reason you would stream it is because
of the size rather than because you want
to send an arbitrary length.
Yeah.
Thing to me,
those are different scenarios for the
application,
and maybe they're both implemented on
streaming under the surface,
but the idea is that you would probably
want some kind of what or something
defining that data type,
and you'd want all the niceties of the
existing request response paradigm, right,
that gives you this stringent typing.
and that it comes out in a way, like,
it's framed as a single request,
single response,
and here's the data type with like the
type that it was defined by the
serializer that was injected into it,
blah, blah, blah.
Like that seems like that's to me,
Yes, yes, that's fine, that's fine. So,
you're saying you correct, correct?
that may be implemented on streaming,
but like I think that's a different user
experience than I want to send arbitrary
amounts of data.
Yes, yes, I get it. So,
you're saying instead of using streaming
invoker rightly,
I would use chunk invoker and chunk
invoker happens to be implemented in
terms of streaming and same for exit,
is that correct?
That is.
That's the direction that I would be
thinking of, yeah.
Yes, that's fine.
It doesn't change anything about my
question. So again, my question is,
in this scenario, what you're describing,
should I always use chunk invoker and
chunk executor for maximum flexibility
rather than using single invoker,
single executor?
I mean,
that's a really good question that I
don't want to like definitively say
something.
Like when chunking was first brought up,
I was always thinking that chunking would
be implemented on top of the existing
request response system.
Yes.
Maybe it's implemented on top of
streaming instead.
But like I had always wanted like my,
again,
maybe this is not even possible because
we never really explored it that much.
But like in my mind's eye,
I would have liked chunking to be
completely opaque.
And then because the whole idea with the
protocols, in my opinion,
is that the user shouldn't have to think
about MQTT.
The whole reason we defined RPC and
telemetry protocols is so that we're not
Yes.
forcing the user to think about MQTT
message sizes or those things.
So in my opinion,
chunking should be automatic.
Yes.
if the payload is so big,
it should auto chunk in the original. Now,
Yes.
if we're talking about implementing the
streaming thing,
Sure.
maybe that's just not possible at this
point.
Maybe it's something we should have
thought of earlier, et cetera. But to me,
the platonic ideal of like a big chunked
message would be that the application
doesn't have to think about MQTT message
sizes.
Okay, so in that case,
are you saying that single invoker and
single executor will be implemented on
top of streaming invoker and streaming
executor?
I, I,
I'm not saying what will or won't be
implemented. I'm saying, like...
I'm really just throwing dynamite in the
thing here.
Yes, yes, yes,
but I am asking you what will be
implemented. So again,
I'm not asking you single person.
I'm asking everyone.
I'm asking what is the expectation from a
user?
How will the user use this API with the
idea that the user wants to be able to
support responses,
which are semantically single requesting
a response,
but the response is bigger than might fit
in the entity message size.
So,
and if the user wants to be future true,
so they, ideally,
we should give them an API that they
should always use. That is correct, right?
It works regardless of whether it's a 1KB
message or a 1GB message. Yeah,
so what is that API? That is my question.
If you say it is a new thing.
Maybe we need to have some kind of
abstraction that like, again,
Mmh.
swaps between,
or we just retire the original protocol
and implement everything over streaming
internally,
Yep.
and then we obfuscate that to the end
user in all cases except for the I want
to send.
arbitrary unstructured data case,
in which case that's so like it could be
Yeah.
presented as an invoke execute versus a
stream,
but it's always implemented with
streaming under the covers. Again,
I don't want to say that that's what we
should do because there's a lot of
Yep.
considerations around error cases,
edge cases, resiliency considerations.
There's a lot that could go wrong,
so I'm not like super comfortable saying
that's what we should do, but that is.
my gut instinct of the way that it should
work from my idea of what would be a
friendly library to use for an end user
in an arbitrary application.
Yep, yep, that's exactly what I'm saying.
So,
so you have a streaming invoker streaming
executor now,
will you have a chunk invoker chunk
executor or will you rewrite streaming
invoker streaming executor on top of
streaming? Sorry,
will you rewrite single executor single
invoker on top of the streaming ones?
That is exactly what I'm asking. So, yes,
please think about that,
I would, I would say that.
that maybe maybe included in the PSC that
what I was asking for.
In my opinion,
there would be ideally two sets of envoys.
One envoy for structured,
like structured data,
however big that may, you know,
could chunk it, chunk automatically,
and there would be another one for
sending arbitrary amounts of data
bidirectionally, right? That is.
Yes, yes.
like your video streaming use.
Yes, again, again, yes, again, again,
I understand. So again,
I'm saying please write this out either
in the document or in the POC that Varun
is asking for one of the others. Yes,
so the primary use case is going to be I
have a request that is small,
but a response that is big. What is the,
what is my user experience?
How do I write such a service?
Base.
In fact, let's come up with, I think.
Let's come up with concrete cases, right?.
We already have that now, as I said,
like one scenario where you...
And I...
Right.
I also want to just be very clear,
like this scenario that we're talking
about now that specifically I'm
advocating for is not what we had all
been talking about when we put this
diagram together.
So it's not that we forgot to put that in.
It is that this was designed for the
arbitrary data case and it was presented
as separate envoys because that made
sense for sending arbitrary data.
If the primary requirement is chunking,
then that changes what the surface would
look like in the way that the discussion
that we're having is. So like,
I just want to be very clear. This is,
I'm only speaking for myself of what my
Yeah.
opinion is here.
I'm not speaking for the group.
Totally...
Yeah,
this document is not concerned with like
Those all.
a message sizes.
So basically there is no size negotiation,
anything. So if it's not going to fit,
then it's going to fail right away.
But then, then, as, as I say,?
I think those are going to be the most
common, most useful scenarios., I think.
Let's take those scenarios and then look
at it from that lens. Again.
The poster.
The idea is that we want to implement
streaming as a more generic form of it.
If you guys are proposing that, look,
adding a checking layer on top is really
the right way to do it,
because the API otherwise gets very
unwieldy and the application gets
unwieldy.
I think let's look at that as well.
Then that's why, Maxim,.
I think we need that, those POCs.
I think let's look at what the
application is going to look like,
what the schema is going to look like,
and what, you know, the...
Data flows is going to look like when
they start doing these stream scenarios.
So I would say let's take these two as
the canonical use cases, right?.
I want to get walls of images.
Oh...
Uh.
Or a streamed response.
I request a volume image response to the
stream response.
And then the OPCUA scenario where I have
many assets and I want to send them all
in one go.
When it says Discover and then I say, hey,
here, here, I found 20. So it's the,
or rather nobody invokes something.
I'm just going to make a request saying.
You know,
put discovered assets and I'm going to
send multiple assets in one go.
So, as of today,
I have this almost the exact POC for this
case. So, nothing prevents you,
nothing prevents you from sending,
Then then share that up.
as long as a single message go through
the whole pipe like a...
So basically,
you make sure that chunks are...
Yeah.
So let's look at it.
Let's look at the API.
Let's look at what it looks like.
Let's look at what the application looks
like, what that API should be.
And then I think those corner cases which
I said,
which we all kind of understand how they
should work.
I didn't list them because I'm not sure
how they should work,
but I'm saying we need to write it down
very clearly.
Because as you guys are currently
pointing out, this is a new protocol.
This is not MRPC specifically,.
This is a stream MRPC.,
So it has some different semantics,
it's going to have some different
limitations.
Add us all those things totally fine,
but let us write it down this hour to
make sense.
Yeah, yeah,
as long as the message size is not a
concern for the parties,
then it's totally doable. So basically...
No, so just to clear,
the message size is not about the
streaming stream entry message sizes.
The message size is about the semantic
thing on top of it.
So like if I am the schema registry and I
Yeah.
want to send a response,
and that response is currently too big to
fit inside the max message size of MQTT,
which is through 50 megabytes,
what do I do? That is the,
it's the higher level, like.
Yeah, Yu.
Problem on top,
not not for the underlying stream entry.
And the max message size is going to be a
result of like negotiation per connection
anyway, I believe, right, with the broker.
So you're going to want to,
like the broker will tell you what the
max message size is.
So it has to be unique to a connection.
Now in this case,
we're going to always be targeting the MQ
broker, but it would be.
more canonical to chunk based upon what
is known from the connection, yeah?
Even in MQ,
you have to do that because MQ will send
different max message size based on what
profile it's been deployed with.
Oh, okay, yeah, then yeah,
then absolutely.
There's.
So Arnav,
do you understand right that you as the
schema registry server or whatever client
you're rewriting,
you don't want to be concerned about that
message size. Is that correct?
Right.
Start.
Alright, then.
So, so that's why I was saying I,
as I would ideally use say a chunked
invoker, chunked executor,
or single invoker single executor
rewritten on top of streaming,
and either of those things handle
Yeah.
splitting up my single response into
stream entries.
And while we may be able to use this
protocol we've defined here underlying
that,
at least with maybe some slight
modifications,
the API we were talking about in this is
not what our knob is looking for.
We were talking about an API for the send
arbitrary data case,
which also uses this wire protocol.
but is a different ergonomic shape to
reflect that the application has
different needs.
But you guys have a document about the
UDP stream and what I'm looking for is an
example of how you would use it from a TC
client.
Yeah,
put a link to the samples that you have
there, Maxine, in the PR.
If we can add those samples,
I think that will help.
I do believe they are there. I'll just,
yeah.
Beautiful, beautiful.
Just put it in the same, I think.
Put it on the same PR.
And I would say in the same ADR as well,
I think that will be perfect.
They should be all ready.
Now, one point that I wanted to bring up,
and I'm going to throw this question at
Valerie,
because it's something she'd brought up
in the meeting,
or one of the previous meetings,
which has to do with the resiliency of
the invoker versus the executor and how
that's different between a stream and a
a classic invoker executor.
And do you see intuitively, Valerie,
any issue with trying to implement
classic RPC over this protocol,
given the failure conditions that we
talked about,
about how like the executor can fail and
come back,
but the invoker can't do the same?
It's true for vanilla RPC as well.
Oh yeah, it is. So like I think it's fine.
I just wanted to make sure there wasn't
something I was not considering there.
No,
my main issues with putting this
underneath is more just about like over
the wire protocol. It's a breaking change.
There's no way to do it without a
breaking change.
Yes.
And so that will be a problem for DSS,
I believe,
because DSS doesn't actually use the SDK.
Mhm.
It uses an approximation of the wire
protocol version,
but not quite the same as the actual
canonical protocol.
Right.
But why are you saying it's a problem
only for DS?
I mean,
everyone else still needs to upgrade.
Because...
Mm.
Everyone else still needs to upgrade,
it's just DSS has to do more manual work
than just upgrade the SDK version.
Yeah, DSS never used the SDK.
DSS approximated the protocol manually.
No, but I as a customer,
I could have written an executor.
Using MRPC that still needs to work.
Yeah.
I don't know.
Sure, sure, like, like, no.
OK.
There's no way to add streaming and like
streaming and chunking without not being
backward compatible.
Ohh.
It's a new API, why is it? Why is it?.
If it's a new API, it's fine. Yeah.
Yeah, we are a new API when we are done,
the only way.
Well, but for Arnav's case,
where he just wants to send structured
data, like,
and it's basically the same as the
As.
request response that we have now,
just chunked.
I said,
the only way I the only way we can do it
is add a layer on top of it,
which is again a new API.
Mhm.
Which says, you know,
whatever different name.
The question, the one on the question is,
will you be willing to recompile your
application or do you want the old
application to continue working?
Oh, you're gonna have to recompile.
Have to recompile.
You'll have to recompile.
No...
You have to, you're OK with recompiling,
right? Yeah, so,
Yeah.
so if you're OK with recompiling,
then it's fine,
because you'll recompile it with the,
well,
to recompile it with the updated SDK. So,
in that case, your API is still the same,
because you're still using single,
it's just under the stream,
under the hold it now sends streaming
misses.
E.
The...
Now, hold up, sorry.
That's what I'm saying,
but your problem is gonna be,
I don't know,
that you're gonna have one schema history.
It needs to support both APIs because
you're going to have two clients,
one which is using the old SDK,
one which is using the new SDK.
Yes, yes.
As long as you can support that.
I'm not sure.
Now, maybe this is sorry,
sorry to interrupt. Go ahead, Arnav.
No,
I'm not sure it would be possible to
support work because that is the point I
was making earlier.
Because if you want to support both,
that means in the server side you write,
you use both on voice separately. If you..
.
Arizona.
Could you take the dependency twice under
an alias?
We cannot have written change,
cannot have written change.
K.
I can't remember if you can do that in
cargo.
Why? I mean,
it won't need to be two separate crates,
right?
You were saying it's two separate API
under the same model.
But anyway, so that means for the...
Yeah,
I think we're kind of into a new
conversation and is what was under here.
Like this is a long meeting.
There's a lot of,
like this has opened up a lot of
interesting discussion points that I
could talk about forever.
I just don't want to bore anyone.
But like for instance, Valerie,
you seem very convinced we'd have to
break API and I'm less convinced,
although I certainly don't.
I am not going to express that I think we
could do it without breaking API on the,
again,
on the chunking scenario for the existing
RPC. Is there a particular reason?
Oh yeah, wire API,
Just wire API. Yeah,
because you have to track the just wire
we absolutely have to break. Yeah,
wire API has to break.
API. No, for chunking, yeah,
chunking I believe we could do under the
same SDK surface, no problem. Yeah.
Okay, cool, cool. Yeah,
I don't want to state that too strongly
Right, but feels like it's possible.
right now, but I am also inclined to like,
yeah, it feels possible to me. But yeah,
Kong.
And.
wire protocol absolutely is a breaking
change in a wire.
No.
But the...
Yeah.
I think the problem is that,
so I think what Varun wants is to be able
to use old clients with new servers and
vice versa.
Yeah, I think that is a tall order.
That's the only way, guys.
It's I I this is this is no option.
You add a new API.
Side by side with the old API and that's
it. Once you have that then it all works.
But there's...
So that means from a server point of view,
I always have to use two on voice then on
the off chance that I have an old client
connecting to me because the new API will.
If you have an existing service,
existing service, there is no option.
If you have a new branded service,
then you can say, okay,
not supported code API.
Or we make it so that the chunked invoker
and chunked executor, well,
the chunked invoker is less clear,
but chunked executor has to then have two
invoice under the hood.
It has to have two executors under the
Nothing like that.
Something.
If you can do some SDK magic, great,
but otherwise there's no option.
hood.
But...
I guess one other interesting question
here. So like,
we're talking a lot about this,
like under the hood chunking.
Are there streaming non-chunking
scenarios that we care about that we need
to support? Because like that is,
you know, more different SDK API service.
Yeah,
which is what we were talking about in
the document.
It sounds like we don't care about that
Right, exactly. But if it's just chunking,
that's a different discussion.
right now,
but we could theoretically want it in the
future,
but we don't need to make the API for it
yet.
The only scenario I can think of is this
asset scenario.
Yeah.
Where it's a weak scenario to be
completely honest with you.,
I know you're recording.
I thought we wanted video for cameras or
something.
At some point.
That going through MQTT is such an entire
pattern that I mean, I don't even.
Mhm.
Want to report it.?
Okay.
That's the media connector thing, right,
which they were trying to make data flow
Yeah,
sending video streams through MQTT broker,
source.
I mean, it's going to choke the broker,
it's going to choke everything in a
minute. No way. No,.
I think the scenario here,
the only one that Mark had was like, hey,
look,
Fair enough.
I find 6 assets and why am I calling
asset, asset, asset?
I just want to send all the assets at one
go and then you, you know, you get them.
So sure, I.
Think we can get more details from it,
but we'll have to make up something.
But you...
I think most of the scenarios are
checking scenarios to be honest with you.
Even is that scenario also not just
chunking?
It is still just checking,
but like technically you can say I'm
sending one asset in one message and then
I'm sending.
Sure,
you're not chunking based on message size,
you're chunking based on asset boundary,
but it's essentially still chunking,
Yeah, because yeah, yeah,
that's the scenario where each where each
But.
right?
From the application's point of view,
there's no difference.
entry in the stream has meaningful
semantic value in and of itself,
rather than having to be combined as part
of like some giant payload.
Oh, okay.
I, I, I guess I understand the difference,
because in that case,
the application is explicitly saying,
like, response dot write asset,
whereas in in the schema case,
you're just writing,
doing response dot write whole schema,
and then the chunking is happening
Exactly.
internally. OK, I,
I understand the difference you're making.
So, so Varun,
are we correct in understanding you don't
Yeah, OK, cool.
care about,
or maybe you do for this this scenario
you just said, like,
because to me those are different, like,
if you,
if if the individual elements of a stream
are discrete and stand by themselves,
that's a separate API from putting
everything together and assembling it up,
that those are two separate APIs.
Yeah,
I think the chunking are P0 scenarios.
I would say right now, I'll say right now.
The 1 where you send a large payload
OK, and you.
which is then fit in one entity message.
That's the primary scenario.
Okay,
so that's the one we target and then we
leave the door open for the other one.
Correct.
Cool.
If you solve that in the first go, great,
and when we get asked, we can, yeah,
we don't, you know,
corner ourselves to supporting only that,.
But we started that.
OK, I need to run folks. Good call.
I think let's rethink and then again,
let's meet again next week.
Oh.
MM.
No.
But if you guys want to carry on, please,
please do. I mean, like,.
I just need to go.
Yeah,
I think I think this merits like a more
technical like discussion with the.
us before we go to, like,
I think right now,
given what we've been told,
in my opinion at least,
I think we need to assess, like,
how viable using the streaming protocol
and just replacing the existing RPC is,
like, like,
and like doing the dynamic chunking.
Like that was always like a theoretical
thing. And.
Before we say it's possible,
like I want to take a deeper look at like
how viable that actually is.
I said I don't want to sell anybody a
dream.
Alright,
so should we meet sometime early next
week?
Yep.
Yeah, yeah.
Tuesday, Monday, what sounds better?
I don't know that I'll have time to look
into anything until Tuesday personally,
OK.
but if I understand that also there's
like time pressure to get this done and
it shouldn't block on me.
But I don't think I will have anything
meaningful to contribute on Monday
personally.
All right, well,
I'll let's set something to Tuesday,
Yeah.
so everybody else also have time to.
I just, because I certainly do need.
All right, Arnav,
you have any other comments, questions?
Not now.
I don't.
Okay,
then thank you everybody and see you.
Have a good weekend.
Catch y'all later.
Yeah, thanks.
You do?
Thank you.
Thanks A lot.
Okay.